Leon Gordon Miller Papers
Leon Gordon Miller Papers
1959-1965
Miller, Leon Gordon.
1 linear ft.
American artist, industrial designer, architect and teacher. Collection includes printed material, correspondence, subject files, manuscripts, photographs and press releases.
3174710
Biographical History
Leon Gordon Miller (1917-1985) was an American painter, printmaker, stained glass worker, industrial designer, architect and teacher.
Miller had numerous solo exhibitions of his work and won awards in sculpture, art and design. He was active in professional organizations relating to art, architecture and industrial design, being a founding member of the Artists Equity Association and a Fellow of the Industrial Design Institute, and a U.S. delegate to the International Council of Societies of Industrial Design (ICSID) to Stockholm in 1959, Venice in 1961, London in 1969, Mexico in 1971, and Japan in 1973. He was a frequent guest speaker and panelist on topics dealing with the arts and the environment, and represented the U.S. abroad in Canada, Yugoslavia, and Israel, as well as for ICSID.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Leon Gordon Miller Papers consists of correspondence-subject files, printed material, and writing. The bulk of the collection is directly related to Miller's work with the Industrial Designers Institute (IDI), for which he served as president in 1960 and 1961 and chairman of the board in 1962 and 1963.
Correspondence-subject files include general correspondence (much of which is related to IDI); material pertaining to several IDI committees such as Fellows and Nominating; and the ICSID General Assemblies in 1959 and 1961, to which Miller was the U.S. delegate.
Printed material contains brochures, pamphlets, booklets, newsletters and similar items, most from IDI but also some material from the ICSID and Miller's firm, Leon Gordon Miller Associates, Inc.
Writings are subdivided into those by Miller and those by others. Those by Miller consist of speeches, addresses, an interview, a booklet on patio design, and assorted other items. Those by others include an address by designer Jon Hauser.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetically by type or title. Within the correspondence-subject series, material in each folder is (where possible) arranged chronologically.
Related Material
has extensive holdings in the area of industrial design. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Painters; Industrial Design; Hauser, Jon W.; Lahti, Aarre.; Miller, Leon Gordon.; American Society of Industrial Designers.; Industrial Designers' Institute.; International Council of Societies of Industrial Design. -- Congress and Assembly.; Leon Gordon Miller Associates.; Artists -- United States.; Industrial designers -- United States.; Industrial design -- United States.; Brochures.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Industrial designers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Leon Gordon Miller, 1965.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - General, 1957-1965 (Box 1)
  - ASID / IDI [American Society of Industrial Designers / Industrial Designers Institute], 1964-1965; correspondence, drafts of bylaws and Code of Ethics, discussion of merger between ASID and ID (Box 1)
  - Aspen Conference, 1964 (Box 1)
    See also Writings: by Miller: Speeches for two speeches given at the conference.
  - Central New York Chapter Design Exhibit, 1963; photographs and a few items of correspondence relating to an exhibit and scholarship dinner given by the Central New York Chapter of IDI (Box 1)
  - Compensation survey, 1961; survey undertaken by IDI on members' royalties, income, etc. (Box 1)
  - ICSID Assembly, 1st [International Council of Societies of Industrial Design], 1959; includes papers "The training of industrial designers" (Enrico Peressutti) and "An international definition of industrial design" (Paul Reilly) (Box 1)
    See also Printed material: ICSID.
  - ICSID Assembly, 2d [International Council of Societies of Industrial Design], 1961; schedule, agenda, papers, minutes, and "Four days in Venice," a journal of the congress by David Carter published in SIA Journal (Box 1)
  - IDI Annual Meeting, 1963 (Box 1)
  - IDI Annual Meeting, 1964 (Box 1)
  - IDI Awards, 12th, 1962 (Box 1)
  - IDI Awards, 13th, See IDI Annual Meeting, 1963.
  - IDI Fellows Committee, 1963-1964; committee that nominates and votes on initiating new Fellows of the society (Box 2)
  - IDI Nominating Committee, 1964 (Box 2)
  - International affairs, 1961-1964; letters from designers and design organizations in various countries (Box 2)
- Printed material
  - American Iron and Steel Institute
    - Design in Steel Award Program, undated; 50-page booklet about the award; text and photos (Box 2)
  - ICSID (International Council of Societies of Industrial Design)
    - Brochures, undated; infiormational brochures from the First and Second General Assemblies; English and Italian (Box 2)
  - IDI (Industrial Designers Institute)
    - Brochures, undated; informational brochures about the Society, its aims, goals, awards, etc.; includes typescript draft of "Company Membership" brochure (Box 2)
    - Bylaws, undated (Box 2)
    - Chapter material, 1961-1962; undated; includes chapter manual, photograph of Ohio Valley Chapter table, "Student Chapter" brochures, etc. (Box 2)
    - Membership lists, 1960-1961; 1964 (Box 2)
    - Newsletter, IDI Dateline, 1961-1963 (Box 2)
    - President's Report, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Leon Gordon Miller Associaties, Inc.
    - Miscellaneous, undated; brochure, biographical sketch of Miller, clippings about Miller, etc. (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1961-1964 (Box 2)
- Writings
  - By Miller
    - President's Reports, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Speeches, 1961-1965; speeches from Central New York Chapter dinner, Aspen Conference, joint ASID/IDI meeting, Fine Hardwoods Association (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1962-1963; undated; letter to the editor of SIA Journal; "Patios" idea book; interiew in Welding Design and Fabrication; remarks about Sigverd Bernadotte; etc. (Box 2)
  - By others
    - Miscellaneous, 1962; Address by Jon Hauser, "Design for management"; "What constitutes news and how to make it," H. Creston Doner; two pieces by Aarre K. Lahti on defining ID and ID education (Box 2)